<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<!-- <?xml-model href="mappingmodcity/2015-10-15-modmap1.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?> -->
<TEI version="5.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May Day</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A trial run of encoding a short story for the Mapping Modernist City project</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>"May Day" by F. Scott Fitzgerald</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <listEvent>
            <event xml:id="WorldWarI" from="1914-07-28" to="1918-11-11">
               <label>World War I</label>
               <desc>The first world war began on July 28, 1914 after the assasination of the
                  Archduke Franz Ferdinand of the Austro-Hungarian Empire and ended with an
                  armistice on November 11, 1918. It was known for its grim trench warfare and high
                  fatality rate.</desc>
            </event>
         </listEvent>

         <listPlace>
            <place xml:id="NewYorkCity">
               <label><settlement>New York City</settlement></label>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="BiltmoreHotel">
               <label>Biltmore Hotel</label>
               <location type="building">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>335 Madison Ave.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </location>
               <note type="imagelinks"><ref target="https://archive.org/details/ldpd_11290497_000"
                     >Drawing of the Biltmore Hotel exterior. Inside the booklet are images of the
                     dining room, the women's reception room, and the banquet and
                     ballroom.</ref><ref
                     target="http://collections.mcny.org/Collection/Hotel%20Biltmore,%20Interior,%20Part%20of%20Lobby%20showing%20desk%20and%20elevators.-2F3XC5813MOW.html"
                     >Photograph of Biltmore lobby.</ref></note>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Delmonicos">
               <label>Delmonico's</label>
               <desc>A fashionable club.</desc>

               <location type="building">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>2 South William St.</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </location>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="France">
               <label><country key="FR">France</country></label>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Harrisburg">
               <label><settlement>Harrisburg</settlement></label>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="YaleClub">
               <label>Yale Club</label>
               <location type="building">
                  <address>
                     <addrLine>Some address</addrLine>
                  </address>
               </location>
            </place>
         </listPlace>
         <listPerson>
            <person xml:id="PhilipDean" role="character">
               <persName>Philip Dean</persName>
               <persName><addName>Dean</addName></persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="GordonSterrett" role="character">
               <persName>Gordon Sterrett</persName>
               <persName><addName>Gordy</addName></persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="EdithBradin" role="character">
               <persName>Edith Bradin</persName>
            </person>
            <person xml:id="JewelHudson" role="character">
               <persName>Jewel Hudson</persName>
            </person>
         </listPerson>

         <div type="prologue">
            <head>Prologue</head>

            <p>There had been <rs type="event" ref="#WorldWarI">a war</rs> fought and won and the
                  <rs type="place" ref="#NewYorkCity">great city</rs> of the conquering people was
               crossed with triumphal arches and vivid with thrown flowers of white, red, and rose.
               All through the long spring days <ref type="image">the returning soldiers</ref>
               <rs type="direction">marched up the chief highway</rs> behind the strump of drums and
               the joyous, resonant wind of the brasses, while merchants and clerks left their
               bickerings and figurings and, crowding to the windows, turned their white-bunched
               faces gravely upon the passing battalions.</p>

            <p>Never had there been such splendor in the great city, for the victorious war had
               brought plenty in its train, and the merchants had flocked thither from the South and
               West with their households to taste of all the luscious feasts and witness the lavish
               entertainments prepared--and to buy for their women furs against the next winter and
               bags of golden mesh and varicolored slippers of silk and silver and rose satin and
               cloth of gold.</p>

            <p>So <rs type="sound">gaily and noisily</rs> were the peace and prosperity impending
               hymned by the scribes and poets of the conquering people that more and more spenders
               had gathered from the provinces to drink the wine of excitement, and faster and
               faster did the merchants dispose of their trinkets and slippers until they sent up a
               mighty cry for more trinkets and more slippers in order that they might give in
               barter what was demanded of them. Some even of them flung up their hands helplessly,
               shouting:</p>

            <p><quote>"Alas! I have no more slippers! and alas! I have no more trinkets! May heaven
                  help me for I know not what I shall do!"</quote></p>

            <p>But no one listened to their great outcry, for the throngs were far too busy--day by
               day, the foot-soldiers trod jauntily the highway and all exulted because the young
               men returning were pure and brave, sound of tooth and pink of cheek, and the young
               women of the land were virgins and comely both of face and of figure.</p>

            <p>So during all this time there were many adventures that happened in the <rs
                  type="direction" ref="#NewYorkCity">great city</rs>, and, of these, several--or
               perhaps one--are here set down.</p>

         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>I</head>
            <p>At nine o'clock on the morning of the <date when="1919-05-01">first of May,
                  1919</date>, a young man spoke to the room clerk at the <placeName
                  ref="#BiltmoreHotel"> Biltmore Hotel</placeName>, asking if <persName
                  ref="#PhilipDean">Mr. Philip Dean</persName> were registered there, and if so,
               could he be connected with Mr. Dean's rooms. The inquirer was dressed in <rs
                  type="image" ref="url">a well-cut, shabby suit</rs>. He was small, slender, and
               darkly handsome; his eyes were framed above with unusually long eyelashes and below
               with the blue semicircle of ill health, this latter effect heightened by an unnatural
               glow which colored his face like a low, incessant fever.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Mr. Dean</persName> was staying there. The young man was
               directed to a <rs type="image" ref="url">telephone</rs> at the side.</p>

            <p>After a second his connection was made; a sleepy voice hello'd from somewhere
               above.</p>

            <p><said>"<persName ref="#PhilipDean">Mr. Dean</persName>?"</said>--this very
                  eagerly--<said>"it's <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>, <persName
                     ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>. It's <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon
                     Sterrett</persName>. I'm down-stairs. I heard you were in <placeName
                     ref="#NewYorkCity">New York</placeName> and I had a hunch you'd be
                  here."</said></p>

            <p><said aloud="false">The sleepy voice became gradually enthusiastic. Well, how was
                  Gordy, old boy! Well, he certainly was surprised and tickled! Would<persName
                     ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordy</persName>come right up, for Pete's
               sake!</said></p>

            <p>A few minutes later <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Philip Dean</persName>, dressed in
               blue silk pajamas, opened his door and the two young men greeted each other with a
               half-embarrassed exuberance. They were both about twenty-four, <rs type="image"
                  ref="url" ana="Yale Class of 1913">Yale graduates of the year before the war</rs>;
               but there the resemblance stopped abruptly.<persName ref="#PhilipDean">
                  Dean</persName>was blond, ruddy, and rugged under his thin pajamas. Everything
               about him radiated fitness and bodily comfort. He smiled frequently, showing large
               and prominent teeth. </p>

            <p><said>"I was going to look you up,"</said> he cried enthusiastically. <said>"I'm
                  taking a couple of weeks off. If you'll sit down a sec I'll be right with you.
                  Going to take a shower."</said></p>

            <p>As he vanished into the bathroom his visitor's dark eyes roved nervously around the
               room, resting for a moment on a great <rs type="image" ref="url">English travelling
                  bag</rs> in the corner and on a family of <rs type="image" ref="url">thick silk
                  shirts littered on the chairs amid impressive neckties and soft woollen
               socks</rs>.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> rose and, picking up one of the
               shirts, gave it a minute examination. It was of very heavy silk, yellow, with a pale
               blue stripe--and there were nearly a dozen of them. He stared involuntarily at his
               own shirt-cuffs--they were ragged and linty at the edges and soiled to a faint gray.
               Dropping the silk shirt, he held his coat-sleeves down and worked the frayed
               shirt-cuffs up till they were out of sight. Then he went to the mirror and looked at
               himself with listless, unhappy interest. His tie, of former glory, was faded and
               thumb-creased--it served no longer to hide the jagged buttonholes of his collar. He
               thought, quite without amusement, that only three years before he had received a
               scattering vote in the senior elections at college for being the best-dressed man in
               his class.</p>

            <p>Dean emerged from the bathroom polishing his body.</p>

            <p><said>"Saw an old friend of yours last night,"</said> he remarked. <said>"Passed her
                  in the lobby and couldn't think of her name to save my neck. That girl you brought
                  up to <note type="gloss" ana="Location of Yale University">New Haven</note> senior
                  year."</said></p>

            <p>Gordon started.</p>

            <p><said>"<persName ref="#EdithBradin">Edith Bradin</persName>? That whom you
                  mean?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"'At's the one. Damn good looking. She's still sort of a pretty doll--you know
                  what I mean: as if you touched her she'd smear."</said></p>

            <p>He surveyed his shining self complacently in the mirror, smiled faintly, exposing a
               section of teeth. </p>
            <p><said>"She must be twenty-three anyway,"</said> he continued.</p>

            <p><said>"Twenty-two last month," </said>said<persName ref="#GordonSterrett"
                  >Gordon</persName>absently.</p>

            <p><said>"What? Oh, last month. Well, I imagine she's down for the Gamma Psi dance. Did
                  you know we're having a Yale Gamma Psi dance to-night at
                     <placeName>Delmonico's</placeName>? You better come up, Gordy. Half of New
                  Haven'll probably be there. I can get you an invitation."</said></p>

            <p>Draping himself reluctantly in fresh underwear, <persName ref="#PhilipDean"
                  >Dean</persName> lit a cigarette and sat down by the open window, inspecting his
               calves and knees under the morning sunshine which poured into the room.</p>

            <p><said>"Sit down, <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordy</persName>,"</said> he
               suggested, <said>"and tell me all about what you've been doing and what you're doing
                  now and everything."</said></p>

            <p><persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> collapsed unexpectedly upon the
               bed; lay there inert and spiritless. His mouth, which habitually dropped a little
               open when his face was in repose, became suddenly helpless and pathetic.</p>

            <p><said>"What's the matter?"</said> asked <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName>
               quickly.</p>

            <p><said>"Oh, God!"</said></p>

            <p><said>"What's the matter?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"Every God damn thing in the world,"</said> he said miserably, <said>"I've
                  absolutely gone to pieces, <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>. I'm all
                  in."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Huh?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"I'm all in." </said>His voice was shaking.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> scrutinized him more closely with
               appraising blue eyes.</p>

            <p><said>"You certainly look all shot."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I am. I've made a hell of a mess of everything."</said> He paused. <said>"I'd
                  better start at the beginning--or will it bore you?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"Not at all; go on."</said> There was, however, a hesitant note in <persName
                  ref="#PhilipDean">Dean's</persName> voice. This trip East had been planned for a
               holiday--to find <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon Sterrett</persName> in
               trouble exasperated him a little.</p>

            <p><said>"Go on,"</said> he repeated, and then added half under his breath, <said>"Get
                  it over with."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Well,"</said> began <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>
               unsteadily, <said>"I got back from <placeName ref="#France">France</placeName> in
                  February, went home to <placeName ref="#Harrisburg">Harrisburg</placeName> for a
                  month, and then came down to <placeName ref="#NewYorkCity">New York</placeName> to
                  get a job. I got one--with an export company. They fired me yesterday."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Fired you?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"I'm coming to that, <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>. I want to
                  tell you frankly. You're about the only man I can turn to in a matter like this.
                  You won't mind if I just tell you frankly, will you, <persName ref="#PhilipDean"
                     >Phil</persName>?"</said></p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> stiffened a bit more. The pats he was
               bestowing on his knees grew perfunctory. He felt vaguely that he was being unfairly
               saddled with responsibility; he was not even sure he wanted to be told. Though never
               surprised at finding <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon Sterrett</persName> in
               mild difficulty, there was something in this present misery that repelled him and
               hardened him, even though it excited his curiosity.</p>

            <p><said>"Go on."</said></p>

            <p><said>"It's a girl."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Hm."</said>
               <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> resolved that nothing was going to spoil
               his trip. If <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> was going to be
               depressing, then he'd have to see less of <persName ref="#GordonSterrett"
                  >Gordon</persName>. </p>
            <p><said>"Her name is <persName ref="#JewelHudson">Jewel Hudson</persName>,"</said> went
               on the distressed voice from the bed. <said>"She used to be 'pure,' I guess, up to
                  about a year ago. Lived here in New York--poor family. Her people are dead now and
                  she lives with an old aunt. You see it was just about the time I met her that
                  everybody began to come back from France in droves--and all I did was to welcome
                  the newly arrived and go on parties with 'em. That's the way it started, <persName
                     ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>, just from being glad to see everybody and
                  having them glad to see me.</said>"</p>

            <p><said>"You ought to've had more sense."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I know,"</said>
               <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> paused, and then continued
               listlessly. <said>"I'm on my own now, you know, and <persName ref="#PhilipDean"
                     >Phil</persName>, I can't stand being poor. Then came this darn girl. She sort
                  of fell in love with me for a while and, though I never intended to get so
                  involved, I'd always seem to run into her somewhere. You can imagine the sort of
                  work I was doing for those exporting people--of course, I always intended to draw;
                  do illustrating for magazines; there's a pile of money in it."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Why didn't you? You've got to buckle down if you want to make good,"</said>
                  suggested<persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName>with cold formalism.</p>

            <p><said>"I tried, a little, but my stuff's crude. I've got talent, <persName
                     ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>; I can draw--but I just don't know how. I
                  ought to go to art school and I can't afford it. Well, things came to a crisis
                  about a week ago. Just as I was down to about my last dollar this girl began
                  bothering me. She wants some money; claims she can make trouble for me if she
                  doesn't get it."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Can she?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"I'm afraid she can. That's one reason I lost my job--she kept calling up the
                  office all the time, and that was sort of the last straw down there. She's got a
                  letter all written to send to my family. Oh, she's got me, all right. I've got to
                  have some money for her."</said></p>

            <p>There was an awkward pause. <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> lay
               very still, his hands clenched by his side.</p>

            <p><said>"I'm all in,"</said> he continued, his voice trembling. <said>"I'm half crazy,
                     <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>. If I hadn't known you were coming
                  East, I think I'd have killed myself. I want you to lend me three hundred
                  dollars."</said></p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName>'s hands, which had been patting his bare
               ankles, were suddenly quiet--and the curious uncertainty playing between the two
               became taut and strained.</p>

            <p>After a second <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> continued:</p>

            <p><said>"I've bled the family until I'm ashamed to ask for another nickel."</said></p>

            <p>Still<persName ref="#PhilipDean"> Dean</persName>made no answer.</p>

            <p><said>"<persName ref="#JewelHudson">Jewel Hudson</persName> says she's got to have
                  two hundred dollars."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Tell her where she can go."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Yes, that sounds easy, but she's got a couple of drunken letters I wrote her.
                  Unfortunately she's not at all the flabby sort of person you'd expect."</said></p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> made an expression of distaste.</p>

            <p><said>"I can't stand that sort of woman. You ought to have kept away."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I know,"</said> admitted <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>
               wearily.</p>

            <p><said>"You've got to look at things as they are. If you haven't got money you've got
                  to work and stay away from women."</said></p>

            <p><said>"That's easy for you to say,"</said> began <persName ref="#GordonSterrett"
                  >Gordon</persName>, his eyes narrowing. <said>"You've got all the money in the
                  world."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I most certainly have not. My family keep darn close tab on what I spend. Just
                  because I have a little leeway I have to be extra careful not to abuse
               it."</said></p>

            <p>He raised the blind and let in a further flood of sunshine.</p>

            <p><said>"I'm no prig, Lord knows,"</said> he went on deliberately. <said>"I like
                  pleasure--and I like a lot of it on a vacation like this, but you're--you're in
                  awful shape. I never heard you talk just this way before. You seem to be sort of
                  bankrupt--morally as well as financially".</said></p>

            <p><said>"Don't they usually go together?"</said></p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> shook his head impatiently.</p>

            <p><said>"There's a regular aura about you that I don't understand. It's a sort of
                  evil."</said></p>

            <p><said>"It's an air of worry and poverty and sleepless nights,</said>" said <persName
                  ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>, rather defiantly.</p>

            <p><said>"I don't know."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Oh, I admit I'm depressing. I depress myself. But, my God, <persName
                     ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>, a week's rest and a new suit and some ready
                  money and I'd be like--like I was. <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Phil</persName>, I
                  can draw like a streak, and you know it. But half the time I haven't had the money
                  to buy decent drawing materials--and I can't draw when I'm tired and discouraged
                  and all in. With a little ready money I can take a few weeks off and get
                  started."</said></p>

            <p><said>"How do I know you wouldn't use it on some other woman?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"Why rub it in?"</said> said <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>,
               quietly.</p>

            <p><said>"I'm not rubbing it in. I hate to see you this way."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Will you lend me the money, <persName ref="#PhilipDean"
                  >Phil</persName>?"</said></p>

            <p><said>"I can't decide right off. That's a lot of money and it'll be darn inconvenient
                  for me."</said></p>

            <p><said>"It'll be hell for me if you can't--I know I'm whining, and it's all my own
                  fault but--that doesn't change it."</said></p>

            <p><said>"When could you pay it back?"</said></p>

            <p>This was encouraging.<persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>considered. It
               was probably wisest to be frank.</p>

            <p><said>"Of course, I could promise to send it back next month, but--I'd better say
                  three months. Just as soon as I start to sell drawings."</said></p>

            <p><said>"How do I know you'll sell any drawings?"</said></p>

            <p>A new hardness in <persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName>'s voice sent a faint
               chill of doubt over <persName ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> Was it possible
               that he wouldn't get the money?</p>

            <p><said>"I supposed you had a little confidence in me."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I did have--but when I see you like this I begin to wonder."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Do you suppose if I wasn't at the end of my rope I'd come to you like this? Do
                  you think I'm enjoying it?"</said> He broke off and bit his lip, feeling that he
               had better subdue the rising anger in his voice. After all, he was the suppliant.</p>

            <p><said>"You seem to manage it pretty easily,"</said> said<persName ref="#PhilipDean">
                  Dean</persName>angrily. <said>"You put me in the position where, if I don't lend
                  it to you, I'm a sucker--oh, yes, you do. And let me tell you it's no easy thing
                  for me to get hold of three hundred dollars. My income isn't so big but that a
                  slice like that won't play the deuce with it."</said></p>

            <p>He left his chair and began to dress, choosing his clothes carefully. <persName
                  ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> stretched out his arms and clenched the
               edges of the bed, fighting back a desire to cry out. His head was splitting and
               whirring, his mouth was dry and bitter and he could feel the fever in his blood
               resolving itself into innumerable regular counts like a slow dripping from a
               roof.</p>

            <p><persName ref="#PhilipDean">Dean</persName> tied his tie precisely, brushed his
               eyebrows, and removed a piece of tobacco from his teeth with solemnity. Next he
               filled his cigarette case, tossed the empty box thoughtfully into the waste basket,
               and settled the case in his vest pocket.</p>

            <p><said>"Had breakfast?"</said> he demanded.</p>

            <p><said>"No; I don't eat it any more."</said></p>

            <p><said>"Well, we'll go out and have some. We'll decide about that money later. I'm
                  sick of the subject. I came East to have a good time.</said></p>

            <p><said>"Let's go over to the <placeName ref="#YaleClub"><rs ref="url" type="image"
                        >Yale Club</rs></placeName>,"</said> he continued moodily, and then added
               with an implied reproof: <said>"You've given up your job. You've got nothing else to
                  do."</said></p>

            <p><said>"I'd have a lot to do if I had a little money,"</said> said <persName
                  ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName> pointedly.</p>

            <p><said>"Oh, for Heaven's sake drop the subject for a while! No point in glooming on my
                  whole trip. Here, here's some money."</said></p>

            <p>He took a five-dollar bill from his wallet and tossed it over to <persName
                  ref="#GordonSterrett">Gordon</persName>, who folded it carefully and put it in his
               pocket. There was an added spot of color in his cheeks, an added glow that was not
               fever. For an instant before they turned to go out their eyes met and in that instant
               each found something that made him lower his own glance quickly. For in that instant
               they quite suddenly and definitely hated each other.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="chapter">
            <head>II</head>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
