<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>May Day</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>A trial run of encoding a short story for the Mapping Modernist City project</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>"May Day" by F. Scott Fitzgerald</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div1>
            <head>Prologue</head>
         <p>There had been <event when="1914-1918" desc="The first world war.">a war</event> fought and won and the <place><settlement><placeName>New York City</placeName>great city</settlement></place> of the
            conquering people was crossed with triumphal arches and vivid with
            thrown flowers of white, red, and rose. All through the long spring
            days <ref type="image">the returning soldiers</ref> marched up the chief highway behind the
            strump of drums and the joyous, resonant wind of the brasses, while
            merchants and clerks left their bickerings and figurings and, crowding
            to the windows, turned their white-bunched faces gravely upon the
            passing battalions.</p>
         </div1>
         <div2>
            <head>I</head>
         <p>At nine o'clock on the morning of the first of May, 1919, a young man
            spoke to the room clerk at the <location type="hotel">Biltmore Hotel</location>,asking if Mr. Philip
            Dean were registered there, and if so, could he be connected with Mr.
            Dean's rooms. The inquirer was dressed in a well-cut, shabby suit. He
            was small, slender, and darkly handsome; his eyes were framed above
            with unusually long eyelashes and below with the blue semicircle of
            ill health, this latter effect heightened by an unnatural glow which
            colored his face like a low, incessant fever.</p>
         </div2>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
